<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<refentry xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0-subset Scilab" xml:id="description">
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>Introduction</refname>
    <refpurpose>C/C++ code integration tools introduction</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsection id="Parameters_introduction">
	
		<para> MicroDAQ toolbox for Scilab features automatic code generation for MicroDAQ DSP from Xcos model. Resulting DSP application can 
	can be utilized in a different ways, it can be executed under Xcos control, integrated with LabVIEW applicaiton 
	and used in Scilab script to combine real-time processing on dedicated DSP core with Scilab script capabilities. </para>
	
	<para>
	DSP management functions allows control of Xcos generated DSP application. User can build, load, read data and change DSP application
	parameters during its execution. Combining real-time processing with script gives flexibility and allows utilizing MicroDAQ device for 
	advanced control, signal processing and measurement applications.
	</para>
	
    <simplelist type="inline">
<title>DSP managment function howto</title>

	<member><para>Define block input/output ports and block properties</para></member>
<para>As a first step Xcos model for MicroDAQ has to be created. Model must contain SETUP block. If data exchange with 
	 model application is needed SETUP block has to be configured to Ext mode and duration to -1. Enabling Ext mode allows 
	 SIGNAL block data read with mdaq_dsp_signal_read() function from script. If model parameter change is required 'MEM Read' 
	 block has to be used in Xcos model. Together with mdaq_mem_set() function 'MEM Read' block allows model parameter change 
	 It is also possible to control Standalone application generated from Xcos model. In order to do that 'MEM Read' and 
	 'MEM Write' blocks needs to be used in Xcos model. On the script side accordingly mdaq_mem_set() and mdaq_mem_get() functions shall 
	 be used.
	 </para>

	
	</simplelist>
  </refsection>

	

	
  <refsection id="SeeAlso_introduction">
    <title>See Also</title>
    <simplelist type="inline">
		<member><link linkend="mdaq_block">mdaq_block</link> : Initialize MicroDAQ block structure</member>
		<member><link linkend="mdaq_block_add">mdaq_block_add</link> : Generate MicroDAQ block from provided block structure </member>
	  	<member><link linkend="mdaq_block_build">mdaq_block_build</link> : Build/Rebuild MicroDAQ custom block C/C++ source code</member>
      <member>
        <link type="scilab" linkend="scilab.help/sum">Link to the Scilab help page</link>
      </member>
    </simplelist>
  </refsection>
</refentry>
